these folks are doing.
I'm really glad
I could bring them together.
You know, I'm just I'm just the, you know,
animal wrangler. It's
so are all of you in Portugal?
I am, yes.
Yes we are.
First one. Of course.
Have you had the heat wave?
Yes. Not
before last, I think.
Two weeks ago.
But not this week.
Okay.
Well, you know, it's been very mild here
on the west side of Los Angeles.
Very lucky. But yeah, it's.
And the fires and that fire in Spain.
Terrible.
Yeah. Yeah.
So quite intense.
But the heat he has been.
Yeah,
but we don't have air conditioning here.
And probably most of you
don't have air conditioning,
right? No.
Yeah.
Oh. Stephanie
Strickland and Dina. Oh, wow.
Scrape.
So you'll tell us what to do and when?
Yes. We'll begin in just a minute.
And I'll introduce the
the track title and the panel.
And then I'll turn it over to you all.
If you'd like me to give you any time
I can put things in the chat.
But it's up to you.
You mean like just a clock marker?
I've got my clock on my computer,
but I don't mind if you do it as well.
I mean, I think that's great.
I'll just open my chat
then so I can see it.
That'd be terrific.
Sure.
Well, there's people showing up
on the screen I haven't seen in ages.
It's great.
And no, none of you are in Florida.
You are?
Okay.
Is that home base for you?
It is. We're in central Florida.
I'm about an hour and a half from
UCF right now, but.
Okay. All right.
And on the east side of the west side,
I'm right smack in the heart of the dab.
Right in the middle.
Okay, I'm right
just between Tampa and Orlando.
And then about five hours from Georgia
and five hours from Key West.
Wow. Well, yeah.
But we are, you know, hot and humid.
Yeah, yeah. Well, exactly.
I was in North Carolina recently,
and it did have that.
Hey, you know
what I love? Really?
In Polk County in the summers,
we get a 3 to 5 p.m.
thunderstorm
just about every day of the week.
It feels like.
That's interesting.
That's that is one of the the benefits.
But of course,
all it does is raise the humidity. Yes.
Well, if you're just joining us,
my name is Petey Edgar, and I'm here to
introduce the Algorithms and Imaginaries
track panel for this session.
This is Portuguese net art and poetics,
and our panelists today are Joanna
Drucker, Sofia Ponti, Rui Torres,
Diogo Marquez, and Manuel Portela.
And so welcome
and thank you all for coming,
and I'm really looking forward
to this discussion.
Okay.
Thanks, everybody, for being here.
And especially to my fellow panelists.
I'm not going to spend a lot of time
in introductions just to say
that I pulled this panel together
because of my excitement
about the activity
that's gone on for, anyway,
decades in Portuguese,
experimental poetry, visual poetry,
and then the things that have happened
in, you know, net art and epochs.
And each of the speakers on this panel
has extensive experience
as a scholar, a critic and practitioner.
So I'm going to move immediately into
letting them speak
what the the program
today is going to run like this.
We'll have an opening statement
from each of the panelists.
Then each of them will present a single
work that poses some kind of problem.
Then we will struggle a bit
with definitions of what's meant by net
art and EPPO, and then address
some of the challenges for preservation.
And I put it in quotes
because again, the the level of complexity
in this argument allows us to explore
that in a way that, to quote Reuters,
is not just freezing something in time,
but imagining its ongoing existence
across all kinds of iterations.
So that will be the way that we move
through the program
and hopefully have a few minutes left
at the end for conversation
with our guests and audience.
Without further ado, then I'm going to
introduce Sophia and she'll be followed.
I'm not going to break in again.
I'll have Sophia
and then Rui, and then Diogo,
and then Manuel, and then I'll again.
As they wrap up their initial statements,
I'll just remind us
where we are in the program and what what
the agenda is that we're moving through.
Okay, I'm going to mute myself.
Go ahead. Yeah.
Okay.
So, greetings,
esteemed colleagues and audience.
Nice to be here.
Thank you, Joanna,
so much for putting this panel together.
I will start by stating
that digital art practices often resist
the fixed definitions, and terminology
needs to be explained in place in context,
especially when we're talking about net
art and poetry in Portugal.
The Phoenicians, for such fields
are both necessary and complex
to characterize their necessary
because it allows for a critical framing
of art practices that incorporate
computational logics into art.
And they are complex
because they are not restricted
to specific techniques
or media or languages,
but are continuously reconfigured
by technology.
So I think it's important to listen
to how artists, designers and poets
themselves, the find their practices
and choose their legacies,
and to consider how those terms relate
to academic and critical discourse.
So anyone interested in thinking
critically about net
art and poetry
should engage with those voices directly?
Well hello everyone,
I would like to focus on a question
that has shaped much of my work.
How do we preserve artistic practices
whose very nature is transformation
and or electronic literature
in general, and net art
resist stable definitions
precisely because of instability.
Stability
is one of their defining conditions.
These works are procedural
rather than fixed, distributed
rather than singular,
and continually continuously reshaped
by changing technologies
and contexts of reception.
My work with digital archives
and Portuguese experimental
literature suggests
that preservation cannot mean
freezing works in time,
as Joanna already mentioned.
Instead,
it involves reinterpretation, emulation,
recombination, and even activation.
Electronic literature and met art survive
not despite transformation,
but through it.
Hello everyone.
Thank you for bringing us together
and I'm very happy
to be here today with you guys.
Well, more or less ten years ago,
my work with the cyber
literary collective Reading
Digital has begun treating the text
of Portuguese literature
as practice based artistic research.
And the collective began
while I was studying uptick interfaces
in electronic literature.
At the time, I was a PhD student in the
materials of literature at Queenborough,
with Manuel Portela as a supervisor,
and our projects often
returned to Portuguese experimental
writing through site
specific installations
shaped by archives by places,
but also very recently
by local communities that live there.
Many of these later acquire
online versions that it is
a thing that we always try to do.
And this extends circulation.
Yes, it may give the work
a longer technical life,
but it also changes
the conditions of reading.
So my question is what remains
when an experience produced
collectively in one place
becomes accessible from almost anywhere?
And what kind of new literary work
does that kind of translation create?
Okay, now it's my turn.
So I love everyone.
Thank you, Joanna,
for bringing us together.
So I'm going to focus my
presentation,
my discussion in my in this panel
on one particular project
that Rui has been coordinating,
which is the digital archive,
because I think we find in this archive
many instances that are useful to think
about issues of preservation.
So when in 2010,
we decided to expand the box
archive beyond the production
of the historical movement,
this is all that Joanna was mentioning
when she introduced the session.
So 1960s and 70s and 80s.
So when we decided to expand
to include contemporary experimental
practices, 1990s to the present,
we had to address a problem.
The problem of how to model and classify
the digital objects
that we were including in the database.
The archive included digitization,
the works created in
many media under very diverse
conditions of production.
One of the specificities, specificities,
specificities of the archive
is to integrate electronic
procedural works with the tradition
of experimental
and post experimental practices.
And I think this is one of the peculiar
dimensions of this particular archive.
The crucial dimension of our preservation
effort was thus dependent
on modeling and classifying all digital
objects in the archive, those generated
from analog works, and those generated
generated from early digital works.
I will briefly discuss how we address
those material and conceptual problems
through a critical design of remediation
strategies, and also taxonomies.
Super.
So as we see, we have quite a wide range
of really interesting topics,
from the work of practitioners
and communities of practice
to the issues
of classification and modeling,
and then the very ontology
of these artifacts themselves.
I've asked each of the panel, well,
we all agreed that
everyone would not present a single work
that has a particular issue
or problem to it, so that we go from this
theoretical realm of of,
you know, critical issues
into concrete examples.
So we'll follow the same sequence
and I'll let Sophia begin.
Okay. Thank you.
So I will share my screen I will share our
you seeing my screen. Yes.
Okay.
So I will introduce this network
that I consider emblematic
because it has contains the paradigm
paradigm gestures that some artists,
designers and poets manifested towards net
art in the late 90s, but also because it
highlights a common challenge
in the preservation of computational art.
So attacking some Francisco
by camera was created
in 2000 and consists of an adaptation
of the classic game battleship.
What you see here is a print screen
on your left of the game,
and on your right
is the game displayed in the exhibition,
a co-curated in 2024.
So the aim of the battleship
game is to locate invisible
targets on a hypothetical grid
before losing all attackers.
So the artwork was originally developed
for the online exhibition
Go to Fresco, a joint venture
between alternative gallery spaces
in Lisbon, San Francisco
and Tokyo, and Kimura's game.
Instead of sinking ships
and aircraft carriers played with sink
art museum
directors, artists and curators.
So, you know, Go to Frisco
was an exhibition that commissioned
37 outworks to Portuguese artists
to be displayed online.
It was probably one of the earliest online
exhibitions in the Portuguese
cultural landscape to be curated entirely
for the digital realm of the internet.
So I learned about this game
when I was preparing this exhibition
that I called
net Art in the Bermuda Triangle,
and it was a very interesting process.
And when Hui told us and yoga,
we were also part of this exhibition,
and we discussed with all of them
how to present the work.
And when we came up with Mario,
we had to face this huge challenge
that he did.
He lost the files.
He had no idea where the original HTML
and JavaScript files were,
and I insisted very much with him.
I was very picky, like,
how could you just lose your files?
And and he said that, you know,
most likely due to obsolete storage
format as well as, you know, broader
lack of concern regarding preservation
and archiving of this type of work
at the time.
So one of the things that I realized
is that these artists did not have in mind
that what they were doing might carry
historical significance,
partially because this type of work
was still largely
situated
at the margins of Portuguese art system.
So what Mario Camera did was
he redid his work for current browsers
and maintaining the esthetics
of the initial version, and we displayed
attacking San Francisco in,
you know, two for visitors to play with
and in.
Yeah.
So looking back, this was
and we also included a poster
of the exhibition and this magazine
where there was an article about the show.
I will stop sharing my screen.
You can you please share my my slide?
That was great, Sophia.
Thank you.
Well, I would like to introduce
Aliya Eva zeal by the Portuguese poet.
Experimental poetry
next to the melody Castro.
Particularly the poem to the poem.
Everything can be said in a poem.
The work belongs to Portuguese
experimental poetry, but
it also anticipates key features in 1971
key features of electronic literature
through procedural
but also combinatorial thinking.
More importantly for me, it
demonstrates continuity
rather than rupture between experimental
poetry and digital literature.
We often describe electronic literature
as something
radically new, emerging with computers
and networks.
Yet Portuguese experimental poetry
was already exploring
in the late 50s and early 60s
many of the same questions.
Permutation, combinatorics, process
variation, participation, and this tension
between constraint and openness in
everything can be said in a poem.
Language functions
not simply as expression, but
also as a system of potential combination.
The poem proposes a generative logic
that already exceeds the printed page,
and the algorithmic
dimension of the work made
later computational reinterpretations
possible.
For instance, Pedro Barbosa retakes relies
these principles in Basic
during the 80s
and later versions appeared programed
in C and C++,
and more recently in JavaScript.
So the work has the work itself
starting as a conceptual algorithm
to generate poetry but written in
the printed page has moved across media
and across technological generations
while preserving its conceptual identity.
It survives
not by remaining unchanged, but
precisely
because it is being reenacted constantly.
And this, for me, raises
an important preservation problem.
The question is not
simply how to preserve an object,
but also how to preserve the process
that made the object possible
and how it circulates.
So should preservation prioritize
original hardware and software, or instead
conceptual and procedural continuity
when a work is migrated or reprogramed,
is it preserved or is it transformed
already into something else?
I argue that Portuguese
electronic literature or offers us
an important answer, and that is that
preservation cannot always mean fixity.
Digital works and duer
precisely through adaptation,
reinterpretation, technical migration,
and also activation.
So change, after all,
is not the opposite of continuity.
It can itself become a form of continuity.
Fabulous.
Okay.
Do you go?
Okay,
let me just.
So I would like to discuss
the family in English family
portraits, a virtual photo novel,
a work I did with Santa Cruz
through the Reading Digits Collective.
It was presented in 2024 at the Media
Photography Museum
and the project Re Textualist,
two works by Antonio Aragon.
The experimental novel book
that we can translate
as a whole in the mouth from 1971,
and the analog installation.
I think it can be translated
as something like
how poetry
in this installation was shown by Antonio
in the collective exhibition called Oaks
80 and 1980, in Lisbon.
So what was the foundational figure
for Portuguese experimental poetry?
While he was living in Italy,
he encountered 93, in his computer
generated poetry
and took part in an IBM experiment
that produced more than 3000 variations
in Portuguese language
from just one group of verses.
And this is no novelty for us
are very different experience
from this particular period.
But when we go to towards
Aragon, what he did was to
use late 19th century portraits
from from the former.
We sent in Madeira Island,
which was a photographic studio
in the early 20th century,
known especially known for taking
an official photograph of the Portuguese
king at the time.
So everybody suddenly wanted a picture,
a photograph taken by this Attilio.
So the photograph selected by Antonio
in the 1970s, had never been reclaimed,
so he gave them fictional biographies
and turned them into a family of ten.
When visitors approach the frames switches
hidden under a carpet, activated
tape recorders behind the portraits,
and suddenly the portraits started
responding with howls, screams,
obscene language, etc.
and fortunately the gallery burns
after a few months
and part of this installation disappeared.
Supporters are still.
We can still visit them.
They are now in the island,
but part of the installation was was lost.
As for the experimental novel
A hole in the mouth,
it gives us another unstable family
and I cannot see one without the other.
Actually, it's fragmented.
Voices evoke several generations from
without
settling into a coherent genealogy.
So our project began in the friction
between these two works.
We did several workshops
with people living in fossil
today from different ages, and we felt
we developed new biographical matrices
with them.
A combinatory process, remixed fragments
from arrogance texts with
the participants memories and descriptions
normally regarding their families.
So these new texts
then inform ten portraits
we created with the assistance of AI.
The final installation
consisted of ten tablet frames.
Visitors use their own phones or tablets
to activate textual and sonic layers
through an augmented reality
app, and later we created a browser
based version that you can see on the on
the superior left corner.
It keeps the work accessible
beyond the Mother Island, but
also in cultures, changes and challenges.
So the online reader no longer moves
between the portraits or places
one device in front of another
as they could do in the gallery.
The voices remain,
but the circumstances in which
they enter the work
become harder to to perceive.
So for me,
this is where preservation becomes retakes
as well.
The browser version documents
the interests of the installation,
yes, and rewrites
the relation between text and reader.
We know that it may circulate further
and lasts longer, but what recedes
is the situated collective experience
from which
it emerged.
Wonderful.
I love this invocation of locale as both
temporal and spatial and community based.
It's really rich to come back to.
Okay, Manuel.
So my example.
Can you see it?
Yes, yes.
My example is,
I think, related to the two instances
that we've just heard about
from Rui and Diogo.
So they are
so was talking about the preservation
by really recreating
the conceptual process.
And in the case of the guy
was talking about this recreation
also of arrogance, early works.
And in this instance, this is a again,
a very early computer poem
produced by Sylvester.
It's a series of three poems
written in Basic
for spectrum in between 1880, 1981 and 83,
and it was later recreated in 2010,
in an animated version
and in the archive.
In the archive we also have the video,
a video instantiation of
I don't know if this is going to run,
I hope so,
a video instantiation of the original.
Poem.
So here you can see that
one of the ways of documenting these
early works is also by
remediating them through other
forms of presentation.
In this case, you are not seeing
the processing by the video
representation
of the processing of the text.
And when we were considering
in terms of the entire archive,
how to create a system that would
somehow have taxonomy,
some kind of classification
that would allow us to cross
all the elements in the archive and link
the computer poems that were being made
based on the early visual texts,
or remediating the visual texts
and the sound texts
into this digital archive,
we had to come up with a system
of classifying
that would, in a way,
cross different kinds of ontologies.
So one that would be more standard
doubling core
based classification for finding objects.
The other one would be reflecting
the vocabulary of the communities
that created these works.
Now, like the concept of poetry or network
that we are using today.
So we were also trying to use
that classification system.
And then a third level,
which originated in our own
analysis of textual materiality and media,
but also parallax or relations
between different objects,
including some of the objects
that were being created,
such as the ones that Rui
and Diogo mentioned.
And so when you
when we look at the structure of the
so when we when we start
to design these archives in order to
preserve or somehow storage size and link
all these works,
it becomes a really complex
intellectual endeavor.
And so we devised a whole system
to think about all the remediation,
all the processes,
all the multiplication, all the.
The big variety of files
that were being generated
either from analog based material
or digital materials.
So my point is that
the conceptual process
of creating a system
like this is also part
of the act of preservation.
Fabulous.
So interesting.
And I think the whole idea of user
generated metadata and community
generated metadata so important here,
in addition to standards like Dublin Core.
So, so many things to talk about.
But I think what we thought
we might wrestle with in the next
round was a little bit
of the question of definitions.
It's implied
both in your opening statements
and in some of the materials
you've presented.
But I think the, you know,
how do we even the terminology
are we talking,
you know, net art digital work,
you know, and the classification
discussion that Manuel has introduced
raises this again.
So if we could talk maybe each of you
a little bit about again,
I know you've all thought about this
in advance and many times,
but how do we wrestle with the question
of definitions of what constitutes
these objects under investigation here.
Same order.
So we'll start with you, Sophia. Okay.
So I think one of the things
that complicates the definitions
in the Portuguese context is
that net
art doesn't belong to a single tradition.
So Portuguese net art emerged at the
intersection of experimental poetry.
It was literature specialists and artists
and poets that started with having,
you know, a computational mindset
and then later visual artists,
electronic, electronic musicians,
sound experimentation, and then, you know,
and of course, computational culture
mingled and start
producing really interesting things.
So there's a cross-cultural aspect
that enforces Wynette
art and resist reduction to either
literature of visual arts design alone.
So it's also important
that to have in mind
that these are digital artists
are not using just digital technology
and not and they are not limited
to creating digital works.
So also the interpretive acts and values
that attributed to net art and poetry
have repercussions
both online in the physical worlds,
and because the work emerges
through computational structures,
you know, interaction, navigation,
participation, different network
environments, it's really difficult
to reduce to either one or the other.
So digital
technologies are not just tools here.
They're the essence of the poetics
of the experiences.
So the artistic specificity lies
in the fact that the digital operates
and brings everything together
in this sensorial experience
and conceptual condition.
Great.
That's a wonderful start.
Do you go
first? Oh, really?
I'm sorry.
Got my alphabet scrambled.
Net art and the poetry resist
reduction
to either literature or digital design.
Because computational cannot.
Computation cannot be understood
as a simple support or container.
It is part of the expressive logic
of these works that we are dealing with.
If we reduce them to literature alone,
we overlook process, interaction, code,
networks, temporality, and procedurally,
all of which actively shaped
meaning as well.
But if we reduce them to digital design
alone,
we also lose their symbolic dimension
language, metaphor,
poetics, cultural memory,
even critical interpretation.
So EPO, tree and net art seem to exist
precisely in this tension
between dimensions.
They function at once
as linguistic objects,
visual environments, programable systems,
and cultural artifacts,
and their meaning rarely resides alone
in text, image, or interface,
but in the relationships between them.
Again, Portuguese experimental poetry
seems to anticipate this condition
through combinatorial procedures,
visual poetics,
and systematic approaches to language.
Contemporary computational environments
on their hand
extend this possibilities
without abandoning the literary dimension.
So rather than replacing it, I think that
we are redistributing literary ness,
and computation then
also is not merely seen
as a technical medium,
but also a linguistic,
procedural and critical one.
Because code does not simply display
the work, it helps produce it.
So to conclude, I would say that
net art and poetry are neither literature
plus technology nor design plus text.
They are hybrid forms
in which language, process,
interface, and computation
become inseparable.
Couldn't agree more.
And there's lots to pull out from that
now.
Diogo.
Well, I yes, I had something prepared
and I thought a little bit about these,
these, these questions of definitions.
But after you ring Sophia and who
I kind of feel the need of a little bit.
So let's see how it goes.
Because I was thinking while
I was hearing you, that part of what I do,
a large part of what I do as a creative
research has to do with the readings
I did several years ago
after those books,
and also after meeting who whose works
and but of course, for me
the notion of distributed
authorship is well placed,
and we all thought about that
several times along these last few years.
But now
and I don't want to I don't want to imply
that this is a groundbreaking thing.
It is not.
But for me,
it is a model that we are testing and
the collecting the work with communities.
So for us, it kind of challenges
to rethink of the notion
of distributed authorship.
So that's where I met at this point,
because we know that after Barbosa
notion computation
cannot enter the work alone.
The community is involved in in making
and making it entered as well.
They give the information
that we textualist the work.
So in many cases,
the literary work is produced through
pretext across media and interfaces.
Yes, but also through these communities
involved in its
making and in our collective practice.
Works by Portuguese experimental writers
are not simply adapt
to these digital environments.
They could, but they are placed in contact
with local archives.
I showed you just one in the island,
especially related with photography,
contemporary voices,
forms of situated memory, situated writing
and then reconfigured through code.
So the interface here is interpretive,
yes, but determines what can be combined
when a fragment becomes available in.
Our readers may intervene in the work.
So we know that digital design alone
cannot account for what is happening.
For instance, in the installation I showed
you, because the central operation
remains the transformation of language
and also of cultural memory.
So the result is this new work.
Authorship
is shared unevenly between source
text collective
participants, both in the workshop, but
also the future readers of these artworks.
And the computational system shapes
the field of all these possible relation.
And this is why I still find the term
electronic literature useful.
It names practices
in which reading with a w
the writing reading cannot be separated
from their technical mediation.
We already know that,
but the term must remain open
enough to include collective
situated forms of rewriting,
particularly when a work moves
between these two instantiations.
Installation browser based version.
This is where I'm at,
and let us keep in mind that each version
changes the social form of the work
and the conditions under
which authorship can be recognized.
So different forms of distributed
authorship, I believe.
Thanks so much for
that, and I'm glad you brought the
readers, you know, into the foreground
in your remarks here, too,
because I think it's an important aspect
of the way that the work gets iterated
and transformed.
There's so much to talk about here,
but we'll move to Manuel,
and then I might make a remark or two
before we move into the challenges
of preservation. Okay, Manuel.
So I think most of the what
Sophia Rui
and the diagram said really have covered
what is what there is to say about
definitions of this type of practice.
I would highlight maybe what
I like to describe is medium reflexivity
or introspective relation with the medium,
the technical medium here,
and trying to refer the ways in which
most works have some kind of engagement
with the medium that becomes
part of the content of the work.
And I think that is a specificity of.
Net art and
in general.
So that would be my my point.
Fabulous.
I'm, I'm going to pick up on that
and just make a couple of remarks
before we move on to this.
The challenges of preservation and
preservation, getting quotes very much.
I'm keeping in mind the iterative nature
of the ontological instability,
transformative nature of these artifacts.
And they're situated within reader
and user experiences
that also have local time,
culture communities attached to them.
And that is to say,
I want to make 1 or 2 points.
One is number one.
I've always been struck by the
concentration of experimental work
in the Portuguese context.
And that work of the 50s,
60s, the visual work, you know,
which again was created in part and dialog
with work that's being done in Germany
and to a lesser degree,
much lesser degree in France and Canada.
I mean that the Portuguese context
really was exceptional in my perception.
And so at some point,
and be interesting to comment on that,
because we have framed this panel
around the Portuguese work,
and I wonder if it had to do with the fact
that there were enough practitioners
in dialog
with each other in a concentrated mode
to really intensify
some of the experimental activity.
So that's one thing I want to point to.
The other thing I'd like to do
is tease out just a little bit
some of the strains that you've introduced
here, because on the one hand,
there's a kind of conceptual theoretical,
what we as referring
to as the the procedural right,
the algorithmic thinking.
And we know that has a very long
history. Right.
Writing under constraint, having rules
of production goes back into antiquity.
And yet when we come forward
into an electronic computational context
that gets automated in a different way.
So there's a shift.
And the question is
it is a shift of intellectual mode, or
is it a shift of production technology,
how those things work?
And that leads me back into these
questions of materiality and media.
And I think one of the things
that because I've worked in a lot of
because I'm ancient now, I've worked
in a lot of different media, you know,
and so it's like you learned to think
in dry transfer type.
All right.
So transfer type, you know,
like these dry letters that you rubbed on.
That was a whole new way of thinking
beyond the typewriter
because you could make
the letters do all kinds of things.
They would break up.
They would, you know,
so learning to think in a medium
is something that I think
we're all also pointing to as well,
which is how the very kind of,
again,
conceptual parameters of what a medium
can do become part of a way of composing
part of the esthetic.
And then I just want to again
push back into our conversation
the notion of situated context and use.
And you know, Sophia,
when I look at that first light of yours
and I see, you know, the
the little battleship
game caged in its little glass case,
I just want to let it free.
You know,
I wanted to break out and run around
and be haptic again, you know, go.
So, you know,
can I think this the issue of the local
as having a temporal dimension to it
as well as a, you know,
community situation,
it's really interesting because, again,
I think the perspective
that we get over time on these materials
is also something
interesting to reflect on.
But those are just my my kind of
summary comments before we move on.
So we sort of said we would talk next
to think about challenges of preservation.
But I also don't want to direct
the conversation too much at this point.
So I'll let each of you decide
what you'd like to say
and see if we can leave,
you know, five minutes for questions
and contributions from our
the folks who are present does.
Is that really okay with that?
Because I've said what I'm going to say,
but I did
feel the need to make a few comments.
Okay, let's go ahead.
Sophia, we're going to go back to you
and we'll move through.
Thank you.
It was wonderful to to listen to you.
I tend to argue
always in favor of preservation, even if,
you know, the works weren't
originally intended to last.
And this is because I come from a context
where little, very little of net
art and poetry has been preserved
by Portuguese institutions.
I've been advocating for this
in the last years.
And and so I also think
I really enjoy how who puts things
like preservation is the continuation
of the work, in a sense.
But what happens when the artist
is not controlling that process anymore?
You know, how
how do you continue with that experience?
You know,
how do you access that experience,
make that experience accessible.
So so hopefully the artist leaves us
with enough information to make decisions
that will always be inevitable,
but to be interpretive and, you know, but
still maintain this close to
to the initial concept of, of the works.
Right?
Again, the challenge to keep the things
from becoming too steampunk
and just look,
you know, the nostalgia for the old,
you know, the old new media, it's like,
oh, isn't that cute?
You know, like when things were
all pixelated on the screen kind of thing.
And yet, you know, at the moment
when those things appeared, that wasn't
what we were thinking right at all.
So I don't know,
what would you like to go for it?
Thank you.
Well, I'd like to say
that when preservation changes,
I would like to say that
preservation changes
not only the technical substrate,
but also the works on procedural logic,
the reader's experience,
and the conditions of interaction.
Taking two examples to classic examples,
migration often preserves.
It can become an interpretation,
and on the other hand, emulation is more
faithful and interpretative,
but it's never neutral.
It can be highly faithful, but
it remains interpretative
because it reconstructs
past technological conditions
through contemporary systems.
But the thing is
that a broken work can still be authentic.
Obsolescence, obsolescence,
and even failure
can become part of a works
historical reality.
And in that sense, a broken digital work
may no longer function
as originally intended, but it can still
authentically document technological time.
So for me recently,
the thing that most matters
the most is practices of reactivating,
reinstalling, and reinterpreting
works that become obsolete
or which are
prey to technological change.
Interesting.
Yes. Diego.
Well, I was thinking of the baroque
when you mentioned the relations
with several other traditions and the way
I mean, we were influenced by the way
Portuguese experimental poets
claimed part of the Baroque for themselves
as a program.
Issue to and structure to
to to build from that.
But I was also thinking of the way
we unconsciously
we are always unconsciously
doing the work preservation.
And I finished just yesterday
an essay on bio poetry, on cuts
and book and a couple of other artists.
So this is a fresh for me,
and I'm going to try to pull that as well,
because I was thinking,
what kind of archive is a poem
that is already on the moon?
And what kind of archive is that?
That implies a poem encrypted in bacteria.
And those were two successful,
recently successful cases.
And this makes us think also what
what in what ways
can we think of this big notion
of archives in the way literature
and specifically
what we are doing with digital literature
always helps to rethink the whole thing.
Regarding the issue of communities,
I did not want to deviate of that.
But when we
when we speak of a poem in the moon,
we speak and this was cut claim actually
we speak a future inhabitant of the moon,
not the present one.
So it's already changes.
And I'm not going to even mention the,
the, the, the Orpheus and Eurydice,
the Xeno text.
But I was thinking of, for instance,
works like the word Claris or Mardi Sophia
that were originally created in flash
and are now accessible through Russell.
Well, the work runs again,
but inside the contemporary browser,
simulating
an obsolete software environment.
But we are always learning from
that work of preservation,
especially in terms of pedagogy.
And this was another issue
that we wanted to we thought of bringing,
because you teach to your students
to see these visible
and invisible things
in between these different instantiations.
So when, whenever, when people ask me,
can a broken work still be authentic?
For sure.
And it is always it becomes.
This recovery process
becomes a form of rereading
and inevitably of every writing as well.
Yeah,
and we have a comment and question
in the chat from Dena Larson,
and I'll come back to you in a moment
that, you know,
sort of addressing
exactly what you've been saying.
And, you know, the tension between the,
you know, the old and the new.
I mean, at what point does
an iteration cease to really,
you know, have an a relation
with its source point?
Right.
When don't you recognize the Dena
didn't put this in here.
But she's talking about the
the interesting again
tension between old and new iterations.
Okay
Manuel to what you please state your turn.
Just just a brief comment.
Just to pick up on what you
your earlier comment about the specificity
of Portuguese context
in relation to the connection
that we can between net arts and poetry
and the earlier experimental poet writing.
One of the reasons is probably
there was a very tight group of people,
very active,
and they pursued their activity in the 60s
70s up to the 80s, and they were keen
to integrate and experiment
with new technologies at the same time
as they were expanding
the concrete text,
the visual tax, sound text.
And so I think
when the archive comes along in 2006,
so it's already 20 years old.
Ruiz project.
I think it really ties in to that long
history of the experimental text.
And I think the I see the archive
as a kind of poetics,
a specific poetics of the archive,
the box archive, and and the way that the
we now look back
at our experimental tradition really
is through the lens
that this archive has provided us.
So I think that the preservation
is very much
a creative dimension of what is happening
in, in our history.
Yeah, I
think that notion of the retrospective
gaze, that kind of constructs
a historical narrative,
it's important to think about.
And as you're speaking, Manuel,
I'm thinking about my own experience
in, you know, with poetics in the Bay area
in the 1970s,
starting in the early 70s,
nobody was thinking in
computational terms, but plenty of people
were thinking in procedural terms.
And so the notion of, of, of procedure
as a generative technique,
and that was again, quite varied
in terms of the people who were using it.
They were coming out of different kinds
of poetic traditions, you know,
kind of avant garde modernism, a kind of
lyric, poetic voice and so forth.
But the first computational work
I saw was in the visual arts and in music.
Those domains seem to engage
with computation
again in the realms that I was, was in.
And as you know, visual
poetics was not a feature of the Bay area.
It was quite marginalized in.
And we could go
into all of the conversation.
But I wonder, you know, if.
First of all,
I wonder if we have some other questions
or comments from our audience here.
I don't call them audience.
Both of them are.
People have been very active
in this field for a long time.
So if there's anyone who would like to
either raise a hand and say something
or put something in the chat,
this is the moment to do it.
We've got it.
There's a pending question by Dina.
Well, I brought that up.
I said, you know,
she said the reactivating and reinstalling
of the works, the works become new works.
How do you see the tension
between the old and the new?
Dina, would you like to comment
or follow up at all?
Actually, sure.
And I was just thinking about this
because I have just resurrected my dead
1999 work, Stone moons, and we'll be doing
a video about how we did that.
It was very difficult because you can't
step into the same technology twice.
And as you guys were talking about
and I loved your talks.
Thank you.
The technology
and even the zeitgeist of the 70s,
and is so wrapped up in that work
that when you reinstall it,
when you have to recreate it,
you're not really recreating it.
You're creating something new.
And there's this tension
about what is lost and what is
gained in a new reiteration.
Yeah,
even something as fundamental as timing,
which I think, again, it's like
we tend to to see the work
and not necessarily address the way
in which the processing speeds,
the display speeds, the redraw.
You know, all of that is part of
how we we what the what
constitutes the work at that point.
Exactly. And then we also have navigation.
My marble springs I've redone three times.
It's a completely different work
because there's no navigation, there's no
timing, there's
no way to recreate the little screen.
The way that we thought about technology
has completely changed as well.
So thank you for all of you,
all of your fascinating works.
Yeah.
No. And again, you're someone who's gone
through so many iterations of this data
and, you know, watched
all of this technology come and go.
And, you know,
you keep learning to think again.
See, that keeps you,
that keeps you supple, mentally supple.
Other comments.
Questions from our assembly.
No, it
must be somebody who has something to say
or some objection to make.
And.
Well, all right. So.
You know, the,
the, the missing works,
what are the things that haven't
been able to be preserved?
Have any of you come across things
that you, you know,
sort of see traces of and think, whoa,
what happened to that?
Where has that gone?
Or for the most part.
Do you feel that the works
that you consider you no significant
as part of the corpus, have managed to be
preserved enough to pass forward?
And I ask this
also in the spirit of pedagogy.
In other words,
do we have a canon of epochs?
Is there a set of works you feel
if someone is going to be familiar
with this, either as a scholar, a critic,
or a practitioner that they should know
and are there again,
the great missing works,
is there someplace another one of the
is there a digital equivalent?
All right, Manuel, and see what
what your expression comes on your face.
Is there a digital
equivalent of that trunk
of souls that someone's going to?
I wonder, but maybe Sofia and Rui
can talk about this
because they're more into the community
and the history of the community,
but I master.
I imagine
there must be a number of lost words.
And some mercifully lost some of.
Sorry poets.
Not everything you wrote is important
to anyone but you and your mother. So.
Okay. But with all due respect.
Okay, we have you some thoughts on this.
I'm not sure if I do.
What works.
Have we come across
that were not available?
Well, Diageo's reinterpretation
of The Familia,
which is an installation
by Aragorn, which is lost, actually,
it's physical installation
with candidacies of portraits
that would react hourly
to the interaction and movement
of the participants in the exhibit.
This is the box 80 and exhibition
in Lisbon at the Galleria Nazionale,
which, curiously, was set on fire
after the exhibit of the Portuguese
experimental poetry, and in that exhibit
at least two works are not one by another
a video
and the other one was a big installation.
We only have screening a very short
screening in the national television.
RTP and Diogo started
gathering this documentation created
recreated in
with local schools and local
students the exhibit.
So there is an interesting form
of resurrecting a work
that was lost, so to speak,
but now becomes visible
in within a different media system.
Diogo,
would you like to add something to this?
Do you think it's relevant?
It is completely.
I mean, we we in the middle.
We learned many, many things.
Talking, just talking with
there were schools
and specially art schools,
but there were also
a social cultural association
that work with communities
that have little access to,
or at least not in the way
we are now used to, because they live
in places in the middle.
And there are they have difficult
access, for instance, and all that.
So we work with several generations
and of course we
when we went to the Madeira Island,
we already
we we had three types of reading at last
at least.
Sorry.
The first one, and I'm speaking
specifically of the experimental novel,
which is from 1971.
So the political Portuguese political
context is not we cannot avoid that.
But at the same time,
we wanted to to bring up
a different kind of political context,
but also we learned that
there are questions regarding families,
for instance, and living in an island
that are still,
after all these years,
there are still alive,
and some of them are taboo and specific
taboos in terms of lineage and all that.
And I want to deal with that.
And fortunately, it transformed all that
into creative into through creative art.
And it was an incredible work
that it did locally as well.
So yeah, but we also had a reading done
in Excel in an Excel files
where we had all the vocabulary
and we were trying to see
how to read the novel
and how to decompose it.
Right.
So this is what we brought to the island,
and we kind of work,
especially in schools,
with this digital literacy
way of creating digital literacy
and a new way of giving
an experimental novel
that is not that available.
Bruno Minister did a critical edition
a few years ago,
but up to that point
it was not for several reasons.
I'm not going to delve into that now,
but so we gave people
this experimental novel in different ways
to reread and to rewrite from that,
not from scratch, but over all the work
that that are already,
already did in that particular time,
in specific place.
Maybe I diverge, but sorry.
Yeah.
We have just a couple of minutes left,
and I do want to hear from everybody
in the last couple of minutes
in the last few seconds here.
But, Diego,
I'm glad you brought up the issue
of using an Excel sheet
as a critical intervention
and thinking about digital media
as a way of reading, not not just reading
digital artifacts that are made, but,
you know, the pedagogy of,
you know, again, analytics, computational,
algorithmic and and so forth
that thinks another important dimension
to the work that all of you are doing.
Again, we have only a few minutes.
We have 2 or 3 minutes.
And I'm going to pose
a surprise question for you.
What's most urgent
in your
own work or what you see in the community?
What is most urgent?
What's most important to address?
Unfair to pop this on you
at the last minute, but, Safiya,
bet you have an answer.
Well, I think it's looking into
into the storage of artists.
And look again to the works
and see if they,
you know, get enthusiastic about it again
and talk to me about it, you know,
so we can map what's there to history,
size and analyze and that's it.
Yeah.
Well, I keep pushing the artists.
Sorry, I think I would,
I would add to what Sofia said
to get the institutional support
to do this, because initiatives
have been by individual artists
and individual academics,
there is very little awareness of museums
or libraries about this issue.
That's a fantastic point and so crucial.
So the artists, the institutions we have,
you comment here for them work.
I don't I don't want to open
a whole new discussion.
But for me being the director
of this archive, it's AI.
There's a lot of potential risks AI models
already learned with the archive.
And the risks include
loss of historical cultural context,
deacon Textualist use of archive
materials, inaccurate attribution,
insufficient recognition,
and authorized reuses production
of derivative works which we do ourselves
but in a very ethically grounded way.
Amplification of biases
which we already detected,
like the Portuguese
experimental movement, is mainly by man.
And so new authors would.
Newcomers are now women mostly,
but AI looking at the past
would probably curate
the exhibits towards more men again.
So there's a lot
of risks involved with AI.
Yeah, yeah.
Now, as you said, it's
a whole other set of things
that are coming into the conversation.
Diego, do you want the last word?
Yeah,
I was going to mention AI perhaps as well.
It's I don't want to ruin the party,
but it is what it is.
And yesterday
we had the keynotes, the first keynotes.
Speaker Yvonne Bertram also raised
significant important questions
on how to create with
and against generative AI. So.
And thinking of what?
Of what I was trying to show you.
And we did some some AI as well. Yes.
One of the things that I thought
was that authorship
becomes more distributed, yes,
but not necessarily more collective.
Right.
Think of.
Yeah.
Yes. Well, again, this opens
whole other areas for investigation.
So that just means we have to have
another panel in a couple of years
and see where all of this has gone.
I can't thank you folks enough.